Guide to the Philip Handler papers, 1960s-1980s RL.11843
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Philip Handler papers
1960s-1980s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11843
51 Linear Feet 34 boxes Approx. 20,000 items
Philip Handler was a Duke University biochemist and goverment partner based in Durham, North Carolina. Collection comprises professional files kept by Handler as president of the National Academy of Sciences, chairman of the National Science Board, and member of the Committee on Science and Public Policy, the latter two being affiliated with the National Science Foundation. Includes many subject files on scientific topics, organizations, individuals, conferences, and institutions; correspondence; memoranda; travel records; printed materials such as articles and clippings; and various writings and speeches by Handler.
Arrangement
Arranged in original order as received, in loose groups of subject files, organization files, correspondence, and writings.
Biographical / Historical
Philip Handler, originally of New York City, was a biochemist and government partner in science. He was affiliated for most of his career with Duke University's biochemistry department, which he chaired from 1950-1969, and the School of Medicine. As a biochemist, he published more than 200 papers on human nutrition and metabolic activity. For his pioneering contributions to the advancement of biochemistry, he received the National Medal of Science in 1981. He was very active in the National Institutes of Health and the National Academy of Science, as well as many non-governmental organizations. In 1969, he was elected president of the National Science Foundation, and continued in that role until shortly before his death in December 1981.
[Source: Wikipedia, accessed April 28, 2020]
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Philip Handler papers were acquired as a transfer in 1986.
Scope and Contents
Collection comprises a large set of professional files kept by biochemist Philip Handler as president of the National Academy of Sciences, chairman of the National Science Board, and member of the Committee on Science and Public Policy, the latter two being affiliated with the National Science Foundation. Includes many subject files on scientific topics, organizations, individuals, conferences, and institutions; correspondence, memoranda, travel records, printed materials such as articles and clippings, and various writings and speeches by Handler.
The files are not always contiguous, but are in loose groups arranged by topic, function, or organization. The files document not only Handler's biomedical career and leadership service to major science research foundations, but also document the history of those organizations, nationally and internationally.
Biochemistry; Biochemists -- United States; Life sciences -- United States; Medical sciences; Research -- Government policy -- United States; Science -- Social aspects; Science -- United States -- Societies, etc.
- Philip Handler professional files, 1960s-1980s
  - Science subject files, speeches, correspondence files (by month/year), circa 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence files, 1977 January-1979 September (Box 2)
  - NSF/NSB 4th Report, no date (Box 2)
  - NSF files, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - NAS-NRC files, 1970s (Box 3)
  - Subject files on universities, foundations, corporations, 1970s (Box 3)
  - NSB files, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Subject files on universities, Associations, individuals, etc, 1970s (Box 4)
  - Subject files on universities, publications, 1970s (Box 5)
  - NSF files, 1970s (Box 5)
  - Speeches, Handler's curriculum vitae, and travel records, 1960s (Box 6)
  - Subject files on universities, individuals, foundations, conferences, 1960s (Box 7)
  - Subject files on universities, individuals, foundations, conferences, 1960s (Box 8)
  - Subject files on committees, universities, publications, 1960s (Box 9)
  - Speeches, Subject files on individuals, institutes, 1960s (Box 10)
  - NSF files, 1960s (Box 11)
  - Speeches, Subject files on individuals, foundations, publications, universities, etc., 1960s (Box 12)
  - Duke University, 1969-1970 (Box 13)
  - Subject files on universities, individuals, foundations, 1969-1970 (Box 13)
  - NSF files, 1973 (Box 13)
  - Travel records, 1970s (Box 13)
  - NSF files, 1973 (Box 14)
  - Subject files on publications, organizations, foundations, universities, 1970s (Box 14)
  - Travel records, 1971 (Box 14)
  - Subject files on universities, foundations, publications, 1970s (Box 15)
  - Travel records, 1970s (Box 16)
  - NSB files, 1960s (Box 16)
  - Subject files on universities, foundations, Duke University, individuals, 1970s (Box 16)
  - NSF files, 1960s (Box 17)
  - NSB files, 1960s (Box 17)
  - NSF files, 1960s (Box 18)
  - NSB files, 1960s (Box 18)
  - NSF files, 1960s (Box 19)
  - NSB files, 1960s (Box 19)
  - FASEB files, 1960s (Box 19)
  - NAS files, 1960s (Box 19)
  - Articles and publications (printed material), 1970s (Box 20)
  - NSF files, 1970s (Box 21)
  - NSB files, 1970s (Box 21)
  - COSPUP files, 1960s (Box 21)
  - Subject files on individuals, foundations, and other topics, 1970s-1980s (Box 22)
  - Subject files on individuals, foundations, and other topics, 1970s-1980s (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, no date (Box 23)
  - Handler's personal files, articles and publications (printed material), 1980s (Box 24)
  - Handler's speeches in binders, 1960s-1970s (Box 25)
  - Handler's speeches in binders, 1970s (Box 26)
  - Handler's speeches in binders, 1980s (Box 27)
  - NAS files, 1980s (Box 28)
  - Subject files on individuals, foundations, and other topics, 1980s (Box 28)
  - Speeches, 1980s (Box 28)
  - COSPUP files, 1960s (Box 29)
  - NAS files, 1960s (Box 29)
  - COSPUP files, 1960s (Box 30)
  - NAS files, 1960s (Box 30)
  - NSF files, 1970s (Box 30)
  - NSF files, 1960s-1970s (Box 31)
  - COSPUP files, 1960s (Box 31)
  - NSF files, 1960s (Box 32)
  - NSF files, 1960s (Box 33)
  - Account book of coal sales (says inside cover that it belongs to Handler papers but not sure of relationship - see CCF), 1908-1914 (Box 34)